let questions = [
    {
        id: 01,
        question: 'Which Sanskrit epic poem narrates the tale of the Pandavas and the Kauravas in their epic battle for the throne?',
        alternatives: ['Ramayana', 'Bhagavad gita', 'Mahabharata', 'Manusmriti'],
        correct: 'Mahabharata',
        expo: 'The epic poem that narrates the tale of the Pandavas and the Kauravas in their battle for the throne is the Mahabharata. It is one of the two major Sanskrit epics of ancient India, along with the Ramayana.',
    },

    {
        id: 02,
        question: 'The Jataka tales, a collection of Buddhist fables, originated in which Indian language?',
        alternatives: ['Hindi', 'Urdu', 'Pali', 'Bengali'],
        correct: 'Pali',
        expo: ' The primary collection of Jataka stories, consisting of around 550 tales, is found in the Pali Canon, specifically within the Khuddaka Nikaya',
    },

    {
        id: 03,
        question: 'The Mughal era saw the flourishing of Urdu literature. Which renowned poet is revered for his romantic verses and ghazals?',
        alternatives: ['Mirza Ghalib', ' Mir Taqi Mir', 'Bahadur Shah Zafar ', ' Allama Iqbal'],
        correct: 'Mirza Ghalib',
        expo: 'Mirza Asadullah Khan Ghalib is undoubtedly one of the most celebrated Urdu poets of all time. He is particularly known for his mastery of the ghazal form, and his verses are steeped in passionate emotions, philosophical contemplations, and witty wordplay. His ghazals explore themes of love, loss, desire, faith, and mortality, resonating deeply with readers even today.',
    },

    {
        id: 04,
        question: ' To whom does the autobiography titled "Wings of Fire" belong?',
        alternatives: ['Mahatma Gandhi ', 'Rabindranath Tagore ', ' Jawaharlal Nehru ', ' A.P.J. Abdul Kalam '],
        correct: ' A.P.J. Abdul Kalam ',
        expo: 'Wings of Fire is the autobiography of Dr. A.P.J. Abdul Kalam, the 11th President of India and renowned scientist. He co-authored it with Arun Tiwari, and it delves into his inspiring journey from humble beginnings to leading Indias space and missile programs.',
    },

    {
        id: 05,
        question: ' Who currently occupies the post of president at the Kendra Sahitya Academy?',
        alternatives: ['Madhav Kaushik', 'Kumud Sharma', ' Chandrashekhara Kambara', ' C. Radhakrishnan'],
        correct: 'Madhav Kaushik',
        expo: 'Renowned writer and tireless literary advocate Madhav Kaushik has donned the mantle of president for the National Sahitya Akademi, drawing enthusiastic applause from across the literary landscape. He was elected as the President in 2023. ',
    },

    {
        id: 06,
        question: ' Rabindranath Tagore, the first non-European to win the Nobel Prize in Literature, hailed from which Indian state?',
        alternatives: ['Kerala', 'Punjab', 'West Bengal', ' Tamil Nadu'],
        correct: 'West Bengal',
        expo: 'At the time of his birth in 1861, the region where he was born was part of the Bengal Presidency under British rule. This region encompassed the present-day Indian states of West Bengal, Bangladesh, and parts of Odisha and Jharkhand.',
    },

    {
        id: 07,
        question: 'Which celebrated author penned the Booker Prize-winning novel Midnights Children weaving a fantastical tale against the backdrop of Indian independence?',
        alternatives: [' Arundhati Roy', 'Salman Rushdie', 'Anita Desai', ' Vikram Seth'],
        correct: 'Salman Rushdie',
        expo: 'The celebrated author who penned the Booker Prize-winning novel Midnights Children is Salman Rushdie.This magical realist masterpiece tells the fantastical story of Saleem Sinai, a child born at the stroke of midnight on August 15, 1947, as India gained its independence.Saleem and other "midnights children" possess magical abilities, and their intertwined fates mirror the tumultuous events of Indias post-colonial history.',
    },

    {
        id: 08,
        question: 'Which renowned modern Dalit author wrote the powerful autobiographical novel "Untouchable"?',
        alternatives: ['Mulk Raj Anand', 'Premchand', 'Omprakash Valmiki', 'R.K. Narayan'],
        correct: 'Mulk Raj Anand',
        expo: 'The powerful autobiographical novel "Untouchable" was written by none other than Mulk Raj Anand (1905-2004), a towering figure in Indian literature and a pioneer of writing.',
    },

    {
        id: 09,
        question: ' What book won Kiran Desai the Man Booker Prize?',
        alternatives: ['Hullabaloo in the Guava Orchard', 'The Artist of Disappearance', 'The Inheritance of Loss', 'Games at Twilight, and Other Stories'],
        correct: 'The Inheritance of Loss',
        expo: 'The book that won Kiran Desai the Man Booker Prize in 2006 is The Inheritance of Loss. Its a multi- generational family saga that follows the lives of two immigrants.',
    },

    {
        id: 10,
        question: 'Which Indian classic features the epic love story of Heer and Ranjha?',
        alternatives: ['Sohrab and Rustum', 'Laila and Majnun', 'Heer Ranjha', 'Savitri Satyavan'],
        correct: 'Heer Ranjha',
        expo: 'Heer Ranjha is the most popular rendition of the story, existing as a long narrative poem composed by Waris Shah in the 18th century. It vividly portrays their star-crossed love, facing societal and familial disapproval, eventually leading to a tragic end.',
    },

]